This is Heinz Lemke at his PDP-7 with a Teletype and
a Type 340 vector graphics display and a light pen
showing PIXIE that he developed at Cambridge
University that has one of the first known
radial menus operated by a light pen. So you, that
cursor in the center is what you can draw with
and the menu items are around the cursor. Also,
there's menu items along the right edge of the
screen to set the different modes for drawing.
And if you just touch this with the light pen,
that runs the command. And then it tracks by
putting these dots on the screen. Now, see how
you can move it around by dragging the middle. And
then you can pop up the menu to select different
components and the menu travels along with you.
And the neat thing is you can draw a line and then
undo it by moving back along the line or just do
diagonal lines and attach things. So this is a
general purpose drawing editor and it's a vector
graphics display with beautiful green phosphor.
Heinz Lemke here scanned 128 pages of PDP-7
assembly language and we have OCR'ed it and
brought it back to life here. Let's see. This is
a PDP-7 emulator with a Type 340 graphics display.
Now there's a little bit that we can do since
we're running in the web browser. We can do
this vector graphics display is actually
another CPU that's sharing the memory with
the PDP-7 and it draws characters and lines and
the user interface can look at those things and
know what they are and like what code drew them
and how it gets touched by the light pen. So,
see this little spiral here, see, I can zoom
in here. This if when you press down and you
start moving, it starts moving along with you.
I haven't done anything yet. It's just a track
and cross. But if you move too fast, it gets away
from you. So, it pops the menu back up. So, uh,
now we can do these commands. S is to start. Now,
that's changed to F. So, for finish. Now, what I
can do now is draw a line. And this is for stair-step
lines that you'd use for electrical diagrams.
And then oh, if you don't like that, you can go
back. Whoop. So this see this is what Shneiderman
says about uh direct manipulation with continuous
reversible actions. So and then you you draw and
then you say, "Oh, I want a capacitor." Boop.
And then you can draw some more and bring it
down here. And look how the the resistor goes
in the direction that you're going. Resistor
And then like that. And then uh there's you can
finish it. Now that becomes your your uh circuit
there. Maybe we can go over here and start another
one. Uh so see how the menu goes away when you're
moving and then comes back. And uh you know these
[laughter] here, let me go back to normal size.
Uh you know there's like a rubber band. I could
finish this boop and then go into rubber band
mode and I'll bring him over here and I'll start
one and then ah now we're doing a rubber band. So
um like that finish. Okay. Ah there's some
neat things you can do since we're running
this emulator. Um I'll scroll down a little bit.
So these are uh panels we can configure. We can
pause the CPU or make it run, you know, maximum
10 times fast or really slow. Oh, the cool thing
is like Oh, look at that. Oh my god. What in
the world is that? Um, that's interesting. So,
uh, so we're running it really slow. It's supposed
to be updating its screen really fast, but this
is kind of neat. I'll have to figure out why it's
doing this. Um, but I've been debugging this code
by running it and finding OCR errors, so you never
know. Um, so let's see. Now, a neat thing that you
can do is play. Gives you a little demo button and
it's just going to play back some Oh, it's really
fast. I'm at max. Okay, that was not realistic.
Let's just only do it at 10 times. So, this is
driving [clears throat] it through the light
pen. Okay, so um just do normal one time. So,
see how you can draw and then you draw some more
and then you move up. kind of have to steer around
the stuff that's drawn because it confuses the
tracking. You kind of trip over it. Um, so yeah,
it's I mean it's very dependent on the way the
input device works. So, uh, anyway, this is sort
of like something you your child would draw and
you hang on the refrigerator. This was actually
Claude that just came up with these childlike
uh, diagram, but that was exactly what I wanted.
So, um, let's see. But there are weird things
that you can do since this is a, um, so there's
a TTY. Every good PDP-7 should have a TTY. Hello.
Hello. Oh, this one has speech recognition. Um,
Help! It doesn't have any
help. Oh, no. [laughter]
There are other programs. Um anyway, uh let me
turn off the speech recognition. Uh so anyway,
PDP-10 or you know TTY can't do that, but we can.
So uh and it scrolls. So uh let's see where was I?
Oh, right. Every good computer has registers. So
and this is the front panel. We're going to make
a more skeuomorphic thing right now, but we're just
kind of going for green screen. Um, so the uh Oh,
now registers are nice, but what about memory?
Okay, what? Oh my god, look at this. Okay, this
is insane. Okay, I'm gonna have to pause here. Um,
what we did is we hand scanned all this code on
paper that we can now single step through. So this
is the original code. This is like a source map,
but it goes two levels. It goes from memory
into lines from source code and we can even
choose the as7 translation of source code which is
a different dialect of PDP-7. So there's multiple
source maps and source maps that go to the scan
and we can uh let's see okay yes there go nice
speed here. So, so it's it's executing the code
and um we can uh we could just like do a trace
or something like that. But uh anyway, what is
interesting about this? Um well, first of all,
memory has the display list. So, these here are
actually instructions to draw. And there's this
neat little thing I can do. There's I added
like normally you have one light pen but
wow I added, there's eight light pens. We'll
have like multi-user stuff for you soon. So you
can edit 340 instructions. So what these are are
little drawing commands and they have relative uh
they you know they only have so many bits of how
far they can move. So when you draw a long line,
see this line is broken up into smaller lines.
And each of these is only allowed see he's he's
like at the end of the leash. So uh but what I'm
doing is I'm editing the display instructions in
memory. So look at that. Okay. So see these this
memory has PDP-7 code in it but it also has 340
display instructions which is move negative -1227 or
so so I'm editing the move instruction and if I go
here it'll go up there and you know it's trying to
disassemble it but um so the the the idea is this
display is a vector graphics display and I can
make a user interface that just reaches down and
peeks and pokes into memory. Um, and uh, so why
would you want to do that? I don't know. But um,
it it's interesting to debug your programs.
And uh, let's see. Speaking of which, oh,
so we scanned all this code and the problem was
there were some OCR errors and then it was like,
how do we make the light pen work? Okay. So,
in 1964, DEC published a light pen test. Bless
their furry little hearts. So, what we can do Oh,
yeah. See, that's all it does. It's very This is
so brutalistic. Okay, we do have a I mean, and
this is DEC's. There was actually a page missing
from the code. Um, so we we we got to recreate
that because it was not too hard to figure out.
But the the thing is oh look see we're we're
slowing it down and you can see it's scanning
out. Um this is just uh it's either SVG or PNG but
the plan is and Lars Brinkhoff has already done
this. [clears throat] We just need to integrate
his code is to have a full uh WebGPU or WebGL
uh phosphor simulator so you'll have the beautiful
fading effect. Um, and that that's but right now.
And what I want to do is make it slow enough that
you can see the beam scanning out. That's the goal
here. So, but anyway. So, so now the light pen
test normally, you know, it's just flickering like
this. And I'm going to get out of uh the thing
is, see, this is procedural. So, there's only
really one line. It's just doing in a loop. Oh my
god. Have I have I screwed it up? Show in memory.
Oh, you see? Um, so, oh, let me show you the
reset button. You You don't want to do that,
but you have to pull it down like that. Anyway, so
we're back. The uh there's a play demo for this.
And the demos are neat because they tell you what
they're doing. Um, so it's going to it's going to
move the light pen around and uh test out all
the light pen. I actually found bugs this way,
you know. So, [laughter] the light pen
test was pretty useful. So, um anyway,
not too exciting. Uh more exciting, more to the
point. Let's stop the play. Um okay. Oh no, we're
stuck in the demo here. Oh, no. Play. Stop. Okay.
Not the world's greatest user interface. So, DUEL,
of course, from 1968. Oh, see see I'm already
I'm in like I'm in um see see DUEL drew the two
um spaceships and I'm not running or well it's
running but nobody's going anywhere yet. So So let
me go uh WD. So So see it's redrawing the little
thing there but you know you you keep your same um
Uh oh. And then bam, bam, bam, bam, bam. Oh
[expletive] I'm not that good at this. Oh, okay. Ah,
so what the cool thing is when DUEL ends, it
hit a halt instruction. So the emulator knows
it's running DUEL and it halts and it can look
in the memory and see like who won and keep a
tally like. So you got this whole outside state in
the emulator that can look in and do anything. So
um that that's how we got a nice you know
otherwise it just halted. See there's the
halt. There's a halt somewhere trace. Yeah. Halt.
So that's uh but anyway so that's the DUEL. Um oh
okay. So I needed to test the TTY. Hello. For
the PDP-7 teletype, I think of a number from 0
to 99. You guess it. Press return to start. Um uh
return. I am thinking of a number. Your guess 50
your guess.
20. Well, we got a little 20 your guess. We got a
little bounce on the thing here. But at any rate,
HILO game, you know that. And then of
course there's LANDER. Lander for the
PDP-7 teletype. You are 500 ft up. Falling at 50 ft
a second. You have 60 units of fuel each second.
Burn from 0 to 30. Time is zero. Altitude is 500.
Speed 1. 0 time is 1, altitude is 410 time is 2,
time is time is 4, altitude is 380, speed is -
30, altitude is 34, 7.5, speed is - 6, altitude is
310, speed is -4, your burn time is 7, altitude is
267, 5, speed is -5, your burn time is 8, altitude
is 220, speed is 50, fuel is, your burn time is 9,
PDP-7 Forth. Okay, Mitch Bradley. I told Mitch,
"Hey, I have this PDP-7 emulator. It really needs
a Forth." And he whipped one out in one day and
it's great. And it turns out the PDP-7 has this
really perfect instruction set for Forth. Um,
so let's see where are we going here.
If we slow this down. Um, okay. So, oh,
and see Mitch being like the Forth hacker that he
is, uh, made a turtle graphics he made a turtle
graphics system. Oh, we're going really slow here.
The demo is not designed to be that slow. 2 3 + ..
Okay. 4 0 DO 200 FD 90 RT LOOP. Okay. : SQ 4 0 DO 200 FD 90 RT
LOOP ; : FLOWER 8 0 DO SQ 45 RT LOOP ;. Okay. So anyway, you got
: STAR 5 0 DO 400 FD 144 RT LOOP ;. Okay, so the cool thing
is CS FLOWER PU 450 BK. Okay, it's Forth and it's turtle
graphics and it's vector graphics and Forth is
like assembling uh you know vector graphics
processor code and then it just makes all these
neat little uh programs to draw on the screen
that you can then edit like this. So, um, oh, but
there's another thing going on. PIXIE. Oh, wait.
We'll do Unix first. Okay. Hello. Login is ken.
Login: ken. Password: ken. At Oh, there. ls. ls.
Here. We'll make it a little faster. Like
we'll have dd, s1.s s2.s s3.s s4.s s5.s
s6.s s7.s s8.s, ls system okay a you got
all that great stuff ar as bc cat mod
uh oh s1.s so there's an assembler there's a BCPL
compiler everything you ever needed I better oh
config here. I'm going to turn for your sanity
we can turn off. Yes. Return lac in one in get
a number of interrupt one source nar zero jmp
one off. Okay there that's a little better. So
we have options. So anyway the thing it does is it
run this is the first version of Unix on a PDP-7.
Um so let's go back to PIXIE. So [clears throat
and cough] when uh what it does, this is hard
to explain. Okay, you know like XML, JSON, YAML,
all that stuff. PIXIE had a more general kind of
uh way to represent data that uh it's called rings
uh PIXIE rings so to speak. And um what happens
is that's different. There's a different layer
than the drawing instructions. So when I Oops,
I better turn off the drawing editor. [laughter]
Go back to light pen mode. Okay. So in and turn
off the memory. We just have rings shown. So
when I drag this No. No. Okay. And I start
and I draw. This is kind of in a in a buffer.
It's just not committed yet. But I finish. Ah,
so what this is is a PIXIE ring, so to speak.
It's it's like Lisp conses. It has a cons, a car,
and a cdr and and it has characters and
data. And uh when I do things like zigzag,
then maybe maybe a capacitor and uh let's finish
that. Okay. See, so I got some more stuff.
This view is just reading it right out of core
memory 18-bit core memory live. So, you know,
you can see there's this double buffering going
on because you you don't see what it's drawing
yet. But then if you commit it, boop. But then,
oh, here we can go play demo. And now you can
see it is drawing the whole thing. That's the
drawing. So, so but anyway, so it seemed to be
this is a nice little PDP-7 library to do this
that's separate from PIXIE. So I thought, well,
why don't we make these things from Forth and I
linked it in like this. So there's the TTY. Ah,
okay. So see, Forth starts out
with this little thing that says,
HELLO WORLD FROM PDP-7 FORTH. There we go. So, let
me spin it again. So, Forth can make these too and
uh the it's going to be able to send these back
and forth to PIXIE and you can run several
emulators at once and stuff like that. But, um
so, you know, the the turtle graphics of Forth
doesn't really know about PIXIE's drawings. See,
the same way that SVG is an application of XML,
PIXIE drawings are an application of these
PIXIE rings and that you could use them to
store whatever you wanted, like a hello world
message. So, the turtle graphics is going to make
PIXIE graphics that you could send over to PIXIE
and edit in PIXIE and then it'll render that into
uh into drawings. So, so but anyway, there's um
all sorts of ideas here. Um turtle words and
uh let's see. So, there is this cabinet manifesto.
We control the horizontal. We control the
vertical. The machine in the page is ours. All of
it at once. Every register, every word of core,
every device, the host around them. Nothing here
is a black box we have to squint at through a
keyhole. So, when something would be better, we
make it better for whichever side is closest. This
1960s machine stays honest. Everything around
it is ours to invent. So basically tribute,
accessibility, and fun beat realism. Okay. So
we, you know, we want to list who made this,
where did it come from, and then we want to make
it accessible for like blind people to use or
speech recognition. So, and then the um anyway,
we're going to we have some more ambitious plans
to model photorealistically the hardware and
even the people operating it. So, let's see.
And there's like a little tutorial on PIXIE here.
And there is a uh tutorial here on Forth how
to use the PIXIE rings and how to do turtle
graphics. See there's these words to to make
things like here. Let's just do this. Copy this
and then go boop like that. And then we get ah oh
look it it added them. Triangle square hello.
So, so he said oops okay is not a thing here
like that. So basically the whole idea is
this is a live coding platform with data
visualization and stuff. So square square
you could even do Star Wars credits. Um,
but anyway, uh, let's see. I think that's
enough for now. So, I'm going to go
Oh, wait. There was Did somebody
I think somebody deleted.
Anyway, well, have fun.